The city shines brightest at night.
Nightcrawler is a crime, drama, thriller film directed by Dan Gilroy.
When Lou Bloom, desperate for work, muscles into the world of L.A.
crime journalism, he blurs the line between observer and
participant to become the star of his own story.
Aiding him in his effort is Nina, a TV-news veteran.
Louis Bloom, played by Jake Gyllenhaal.
Rick, played by Riz Ahmed.
Nina Romina, played by Rene Russo.
Joe Loder, played by Bill Paxton.
Frank Kruse, played by Kevin Rahm.
Detective Frontieri, played by Michael Hyatt.
Nightcrawler is a 2014 American neo-noir crime thriller film written
and directed by Dan Gilroy in his directorial debut.
It stars Jake Gyllenhaal as an unhinged stringer who seeks out violent and morbid events late at night in Los
Angeles so he can film them and sell the exclusive footage to a local television news station.
The supporting cast includes Rene Russo, Riz Ahmed, and Bill Paxton.
Gilroy originally wanted to make a film about the life of American photographer Weegee, but switched focus
after discovering the unique narrative possibilities surrounding the stringer profession.
He wrote the protagonist as an antihero, based on the ideas of unemployment and capitalism; a common theme
in the film is the symbiotic relationship between unethical journalism and consumer demand.
Gyllenhaal served as a producer on the film and played a pivotal role in its creation, becoming
involved in choosing members of the crew and watching other actors' audition tapes.
Filming was a challenging process, taking place across 80
locations over the course of four weeks.
Open Road Films utilized viral marketing to promote Nightcrawler, including a fictional
video résumé on Craigslist and fake social media profiles for the protagonist.
The film premiered at the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival on September 15 and was released theatrically on October 31,
going on to gross $50.3 million against a budget of $8.5 million and gaining a cult following in the process.
It was met with widespread praise, especially Gilroy's
screenplay and the performances of Gyllenhaal and Russo.
Several critics listed Nightcrawler as one of the best films of 2014 and it received various
accolades, including a Best Original Screenplay nomination at the 87th Academy Awards.
Gyllenhaal was nominated as Lead Actor for the BAFTA Award, Screen Actors Guild Award, Golden Globe Award and Critics'
Choice Movie Award, with his non-nomination in the Best Actor Oscar category considered by many to be a snub.
The film explores themes of underground, psychopath,
journalism, job interview, cynicism.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.